<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="./_c74_tut.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<chapter name="Quintet.net: Manual">

<!--<setdocpatch name="02jJavascriptScripting" patch="02jJavascriptScripting.maxpat"/>-->
<previous name="02components">Quintet.net: Intro</previous>
<next name="04tutorial">Quintet.net: Tutorial</next>
<parent name="00index">Quintet.net: Table of Contents</parent>

<h1>Quintet.net</h1>

<h2><b>Manual</b></h2>

<h2><b>Composing for Quintet.net</b></h2>


<p>The music performed with Quintet.net is typically a combination of composed and improvised elements. Before the advent of broadband low-latecy networks, the lack of real synchronicity necessitated the adaptation of a genuine “Internet” performance style for which John Cage’s number pieces were considered a model: These pieces require certain notes or phrases to be played within “time brackets.”</p>

<h2><b>Getting Started</b></h2>

<p>We are going to jump-start Quintet.net by launching all the components on one machine and running Five by John Cage, the "Hello World" of Quintet.net. Once we’ve covered the basics of Quintet.net, we are going to look at the Tutorial project which will give an overview of how to compose for the environment. After a successful installation, the Quintet.net folder should reside in the Max 8/Packages folder. Please don’t move this folder or its subfolders, since, otherwise, Quintet.net may not function properly.</p>

<h2><b>Launching the Quintet.net components</b></h2>

<p>First launch either the Max application. Now, let’s open three components, one at a time. N.B. Quintet.net was designed so that one (and only one) copy of each component can run in one instance of Max. Launching several copies of a component will lead to erratic behavior.</p>
<p>Let’s start by first opening the Quintet.net Server 2020 and then the Quintet.net Client 2020. You'll find the components in the Quintet.net Package. For the Server, please first select the network connection it is supposed to listen to. This can be your loopback connection (lo0) or the Ethernet adapter (typically en0). Then start the Server and launch the Client.</p>
<p><illustration><img src="images/Toolbar.png"/></illustration></p>

<p>
Once the Client has opened, fill in your name, location and identity (choose Player 1, for simplicity's sake). Now, click on the red double-arrow button on the top right-hand side in order to log onto the server. The button should turn green, if successful. The Server displays the IP number:return port info as well as the name and the location for each participant.</p>
<p>Click on yellow Preferences button on the top left-hand side, click on the Project icon in the Preferences window and select Five from the List of stored Projects. This will load the sound files and a few other project-specific resources.</p>
<p><illustration><img src="images/Preferences.png"/></illustration></p>

<p>
Let’s return to the Client. Turn on audio by clicking on the Power icon in the middle of the tool bar. It should turn blue. On the left hand side you’ll see a number of pop-up menus. For your staff, choose the instrument “3angle” from the “Instrm.” menu and start typing on the keyboard. </p>
<p>At this point, quarter-note heads should appear on the staff and you should hear a sound provided that you hold the key long enough (the sounds used for “Five” fade in slowly). If the sound is too soft, click on the “Preferences” button and on the “Audio Levels” tab. Adjust the fader that corresponds to your staff. In rare cases, if you don’t hear any sound, you may have to press the return key to reset the sampler.</p>
<p>Of course, you can always attach a MIDI keyboard. First make sure that MIDI is enabled in the Input list, and then set the correct MIDI input port in the MIDI pane of the Preferences window.

</p>
<h2><b>Keyboard Layout and Tunings</b></h2>

<p>The computer keyboard can be used as an polyphonic instrument. It should always be set to U.S. or British, unless you care to create your own map. (Examples can be found in: "Max 8/Packages/Quintet.net/patchers/Library/Data/Keyboard Layout/".) This keyboard layout will be different when you choose a different tuning from the “Tuning” menu. All tunings have in common that middle c is always assigned to “q”. You may also want to experiment a bit with the Tuning, Process and Filter menus.</p>

<h2><b>Working with a conductor</b></h2>

<p>It’s time to launch Quintet.net Conductor 2020.</p>

<p>If you launch the Conductor for the first time, you probably won’t see a control panel in the bottom part of the window. This is because no compositions have been saved with the Conductor preferences yet. Register the Conductor just as you did with the Client by clicking on the red connect button AFTER entering your name and your address. Open the project called Five (the same way we did in the previous section). All changes made to the “Display”, “Instrument”, “Tuning”, “Process” and “Filter” menus by the Conductor should instantaneously be reflected by the Clients and vice versa.</p>
<p>Next, we want to start the piece. Follow the sequence of buttons in left to right order in the Five control panel to execute the following functions:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Initialize: Send the initial settings to the Clients</li>
  <li>Send Score: The score will now display on the Clients</li>
  <li>Start: Start the counter and send a sequence of message to the Clients</li>
  <li>Page 1, 2 and 3: Jump to the indicated page in the score and click on start to resume counter</li>
  <li>Stop: Stop sequence</li>

</ul>

<p>This piece can either be performed on the Internet with acoustic instrument via low-latency audio streaming or by playing the built-in sampler using a MIDI controller or simply the computer keyboard. In the score, the characters on top of the notes refer to the keys to be pressed in this particular input mode (U.S. keyboard layout). In this piece by Cage, one of his Number pieces, events take place within time brackets. The players are free to start and end the note(s) as long as they are within the times given on top of the score. Notes should be played legato when tied and clearly separated when followed by a breathmark. Currently, the computer keyboard has two dynamic levels mp and f. In order to play the notes f, the shift key has to be pressed as well.</p>

<h2><b>Viewer</b></h2>

<p>While the graphical output in the Client window was designed to give the players and the listeners visual feedback on musical and control events, the Viewer uses the Jitter graphical environment for the creation of a visual layer complementing a Quintet.net performance.

To demonstrate some basic features of the Viewer, the score of Five will be displayed. Launch Quintet.net Viewer 2020 and register the component with the Quintet.net Server. Then click the “Load Settings...” button and locate the Five.viewer.xml file in the Five project folder. Press shift-return to load the first preset. During a performance, the Conductor can be programmed to take care of this, but it's a good idea to try this first manually. In the Viewer preferences, set the video resolution to resonable numbers corresponding to the aspect ratio of your projector or screen (a second screen is strongly recommended when working with the Viewer), move the Quintet.net window to the other screen and press "esc", which will put the Viewer in full-screen mode.

Now start the piece in the Conductor and verify that the page turns happen as expected.</p>

<!--
<seealsolist>
<seealso name="js">Max JavaScript object</seealso>
<seealso name="jsintro" type="vignette" module="js" >javascriptinmax</seealso>
</seealsolist>
-->
</chapter>
